A Guide to the Papers of Howard W. Smith 1920-1976
Special Collections, University of Virginia Library
Special Collections, University of Virginia Library
Papers of Howard W. Smith 1920-1976
Special Collections, University of Virginia Library
8731-c
This collection consists of 850 items.
Administrative Information
Access Restrictions
There are no restrictions.
Acquisition Informatin
This collection was a gift of Howard W. Smith, June 7, 1978.
Scope and Content
The papers contain correspondence, oral history interviews with Smith, and memoranda by Smith, 1966-1973, compiled by several researchers for projected books on changes in the American constitutional system during Smith's years in Congress. There are also letters of condolence to Mrs. Smith on her husband's death, including one from Gerald Ford.
Of interest in his correspondence is an exchange with Frederick Deane Goodwin Ribble on the constitutionality of Federal troops in the 1957 Little Rock crisis, a letter from Sargent Shriver justifying the Peace Corps, and a telegram, 1964, from Carl Albert asking Smith's committee to hear the anti-povery bill. Speeches, 1953-1968, given or written by Smith, are included.
Most of the collection consists of memorabilia from a 1951 visit of a Congressional delegation to the Council of Europe in Strasbourg, preceded by official visits to West Germany and Austria.
Photographs, clippings, invitations, guest books, articles about Smith, and a list of his constituents and supporters from an election campaign complete the collection.
Arrangement
The collection is arranged in five series: I. Correspondence; II. Speeches; III. Memorabilia; IV. Printed Material; and, V. Photographs. Within each series material is arranged by topic and subarranged chronologically in each folder.
Contents List
- Series I. Correspondence
  - Correspondence on various topics 1920-1975 (Box 1)
  - Correspondence concerning the American Enterprise Institute oral history project 1977 Nov. 21-1970 Dec. 4, (5 folders) (Box 1)
    Includes correspondence, transcripts and related material.
  - Correspondence with the Institute for Humane Studies 1973 (Box 1)
    Concerning interviews for possible history project.
  - Correspondence concerning the oral history project of B. Murtha and Doug Trussell 1973 (Box 1)
  - Letters of condolence to Mrs. Smith upon the death of Howard W. Smith 1976 (Box 1)
- Series II. Speeches
  - Speeches 1933-1966 (Box 2)
  - Speeches and memoranda 1967-1968 (Box 2)
    Includes speeches by Smith and others.
- Series III. Memorabilia
  - Strasbourg Conference 1951, (5 folders) (Box 2)
  - Memorabilia re Strasbourg Conference 1951 (Box 4)
  - Invitations 1953-1957 (Box 2)
  - Invitations to White House events 1955-1970 (Box 2)
  - Invitations, tickets, etc. to 1957, 1961 and 1969 Presidential inaugurations 1957-1969 (Box 2)
  - Guest book 1957 Oct. 9 (Box 3)
  - Guest books for 1960 and for Smith's birthday, 1961 1960-1961 (Box 3)
  - List of constituents and supporters n.d. (Box 3)
  - Miscellaneous n.d. (Box 3)
- Series IV. Printed Material
  - Magazine articles and tv and radio transcripts by or about Smith 1940-1964 (Box 3)
  - Clippings 1933-1976, (3 folders) (Box 3)
  - Menus of cruise, Strasbourg Conference 1951 (Box 4)
  - Miscellaneous n.d. (Box 3)
- Series V. Photographs
  - Photographs [ca.1906-1907] (Box 4)
  - Strasbourg Conference 1951 (Box 3)
  - Photograph album of Strasbourg Conference 1951 (Box 4)
  - Miscellaneous n.d. (Box 3)